howdy this is Jim rut and this is the
Jim rut show listeners have asked us to
provide pointers some of the resources
we talked about on the show we now have
links to books and articles referenced
in recent podcasts that are available on
our website
we also offer full transcripts go to Jim
rut show.com that's Jim ruts show com
this is another in our series of extra
covered 19 interviews and as on the
other extra interviews the audio quality
will not be up to our normal standards
but the information will be of the usual
high quality
today's guest is Jessica flack resident
faculty at the Santa Fe Institute as
she's been on the show before and she's
an incredibly good thinker about complex
systems interactions between cause at
cause and effect there are lots of other
interesting things she has some
interesting ideas about how the shock to
the system from koban 19 may actually
provide some opportunities to move our
world to a better place
so with that Jessica let tell us about
your thinking well I mean I guess I just
want to start I know you thought about
this too she there should be a fun
discussion but I just wanted to start by
making this point I think we're at a
kind of unique moment in history in the
following sense when ever before and
it's two hundred thousand years and Homo
sapiens have essentially walked the
earth has there been what I would call a
collective empirically informed global
response of the magnitude that we're
seeing with this Cova nineteen crisis so
I don't think there's another example
when we've seen basically all nations or
more or less all nations simultaneously
faint face the same immediate threat and
what's so interesting about this is that
the response it's been one at one
simultaneously chaotic and and full of
promise and that might sound
inappropriate given you know that this
is causing lots of hardship and it's
quite tragic for many people but
I think there are opportunities here
that can be exploited to perhaps tip
society into a better future and I'll
just say a few more things before
letting you jump in and that is you know
I mean from the low-hanging fruit point
of view we're seeing innovation in our
understanding of obviously epidemiology
and viral dynamics and and maybe even in
the character of science scientific
collaboration and and we have the
opportunity to better understand how
massive environmental events influence
the robustness and trajectory of coupl
systems like markets and economies but
there's also something much more
profound potentially on the table and
that's that perturbations I think like
this virus can potentially reveal new
approaches or show that value of old
approaches did as may be out of reach or
nonsensical given the status quo and so
like as just an example we can get into
many more you know many more ideas
one example is you know I think we're
developing an intuition that was kind of
before academic for the costs and
benefits of say democratic bottom-up
american-style capitalism and say
Chinese top-down kind of capitalism an
intuition that we just didn't have
before because we couldn't see the
effects sort of in real time playing out
and of course that's very noisy and we
have biases and it needs to be worked
out empirically but but we're seeing
maybe for the first time how certain
kinds of changes are driven for example
by the institutions and social
structures that we have in place much
more clearly than in the past
yeah the way of framing I've been using
for these discussions about impact of
kovat on the future is in the form of
trying to look at where will homeostasis
dominate and where will hysteresis
dominate for our audience homeostasis is
a tendency for complex systems to return
to their previous state after a shock
for instance you get the get a cold you
know you feel like for three days
ten days later you're just fine I'm very
little changes happen to you a little
bit at the serological level but nothing
material the other hand you put a bullet
through your heart the homeostasis
doesn't work anymore
and that event totally dominates the
future and of course that's an extreme
example there's lots of other more
modest examples and so we think about
the complex dynamical networks that are
our society everything from the economy
to education to marriage to friendship
to scientific work now this is a big
shock you know I liked your framing this
is the biggest coordinated action by the
human race ever
almost certainly I can't it's got to be
true I would also warrant een many
orders I was you yeah by many words
Matthew it's also I would argue the
biggest shock at least to the West since
world war two and that's pretty damn big
shock so and and it had all kinds of
downstream effects so yeah I think we
will see some reach attempts to return
the way things are but there will also
be things that will be more naturally
knocked out of their current basin of
Attraction and into a new one and let's
explore some of your ideas there I think
those are some of the most important and
most profound things that will come out
of this yeah so I don't turn that on its
head a little bit and ask this question
so we in when we think about what we
want how we want our society to be
structured and what we want to optimize
assuming you know or satisfice we often
talk about the degree of inequality or
you know fairness or whatever side of
the spectrum you fall with respect to
these issues but we talk about specific
outcomes that we would like to see and
one of the things I've been wondering
about is if instead of building
societies designed to maximize or
minimize certain things like the degree
of inequality could we build a society
that instead optimized or satisfies for
robustness and evolved ability and what
would it mean how would we have to
change things in order to be optimizing
for those things as opposed to specific
outcomes and I'm not saying that we
right now have the capacity to really
optimize even satisfies for inequality
of the level of inequality right I don't
I don't think that's something that we
can very well control but it's the kind
of discussion that we as a society have
all the time
and in
saying what if we switch focus not you
know away from specific outcomes and
Turin towards tuning mechanisms that
allow us to change how a robust and I'm
available we are given what's going on
in in the larger world whether it's
ecological or social yeah that makes a
huge amount of sense and you know like a
lot of people are starting to think that
way because you know one of the things
I've pointed out again and again is that
this pen are a pandemic with the
statistical attributes of this one were
entirely predictable if one understands
the fact that pandemics are fat-tailed
phenomena and you plot some of the
pandemics we've had over the last 50
years one of this scale is it's just
going to happen and oh by the way this
is not way out on the right tail there
will be pandemics a lot worse than this
one and I think it highlights in fact it
shows the amazing stupidity of the
hardcore game a money on money return
world that works for short term
efficiency and essentially tends to
never invest except at gunpoint in
robustness and resilience you know a
tiny investment a couple hundred million
dollars in January by the United States
government in ramping up masks and
ventilator production beginning the you
know some at scale run-up of testing
because so we wouldn't have had that
first run debacle of testing its after a
tiny tiny investment on the scale of
things probably would have cut the
economic cost of this by a couple of
trillion dollars and yet there is no
signal within our current social systems
that allows that to happen right but
that's true and I think I don't I guess
we have to ask it's like what would it
mean to build society that could more
fluidly respond to these kinds of events
and also be working when you know
everything was running well so for
example I mean just think outside my
head I imagine that we would invest in
technology like 3d printers or whatever
the version you know 3d printer 2.0 that
could produce infrastructure ventilators
and so forth at scale when on demand
essentially and in that way you know
allow us to have a more and hopefully
out of materials that are biodegradable
right because if we're gonna produce
materials that we only need during a
crisis and and we have nowhere to store
them or you know we want we don't want
to cause problems so how could we you
know what are the what are the points of
entry into a system where you're
optimizing for robustness and
evolvability and not specific outcomes
it or not like you say so how will you
focus on efficiency what are the things
we would need to change to do that yep
knowledge of you want what do we want to
be investing what kinds of educational
systems would we want to be investing
and maybe for example and this is you
know everyone's talking about this not
to education that focuses on
probabilistic thinking right as opposed
to you know learning just standard
statistics and calculus in high school
and you know the other one it's just
amazing the general public has no
intuition on Exponential's it's a
staggering to me one of the things that
we were talking about before the show
was the cognitive difference is how
people have behaved under the
information flowing out about koban 19
and I've come to conclusion that there's
a huge line between those who have a
good intuition about what an exponential
is and those that don't so that's
another part of our educational toolkit
but I would go beyond just technology
and hard preparedness I would say that
this has also highlighted a major flaw
in our information processing you know
there was early signal that was
available to intelligence services in
the West by mid to late December at that
point you know especially knowing about
the fat-tailed nature of pandemics small
bets should have been placed to get
ready tens of millions of dollars in the
United States context in January should
have been hundreds of millions of
dollars but the information the signal
did not get through the noise and did
not get to sense makers and then
decision takers and then action makers
and so when I think we have to really
think through and
not just in stuff like 3d printers and
flexible manufacturing but a more robust
form of signal capture since making
decision making and then mobilization
for action that may be the thing that
gives us the greatest ability to operate
dynamically and in the evolutionary
context where we don't necessarily know
what the next big threats gonna be yeah
I mean I think that this is one of the
one of the points I like to make is that
when we do have these heavy tail
distributions the the they're sorted
they're different than normal
distribution and or they're the same as
a normal distribution in the sense that
there's a lot of things that are more or
less similar to each other they're in
the bulk but there are a few things on
the tail that are rare but much more
much bigger than you would see in a
normal distribution but and they're rare
but less rare than they would be in a
normal distribution that's important and
one of the things that we see so there
there are low probability significant
events one of the things that we see
when those events occur is that there
are second-order events in the tail that
are almost impossible to predict ahead
of time because they require the first
order tail events to have occurred and
then their likelihood increases and so
these are not things that we can
forecast really but they're scenarios
that we can prepare for and we can have
strategies if we know we're entering
into you know if we're in a first order
tail event we know that certain kinds of
behavioral shifts that make the
second-order tail events more likely we
know what they are and so we can check
our own behavior so these are not things
we can forecast but we can set up
scenarios or a scenario space and
understand or develop a set of
strategies for dealing in those
scenarios and I think we need to see a
lot more of that absolutely in fact one
of ideas I'm going to propose I'm gonna
do it here for the first time I've been
taking some notes to myself I'm gonna
write a little essay on it is the US
government should establish an executive
department of wicked risks whose job it
is to do just this kind of stuff who
basically do advance scenario planning
for the civil civilian sector to
probabilistic modeling who wargame Red
Team responses to theoretical things
like for rinse
it would have been really nice if we
could take an bribe them if necessary
you know a medium-sized city a hundred
thousand people and literally run a live
drill what happens if you have a
pandemic of this statistical attribute
we would have found all kinds of things
like oh we don't have enough mass
we run out of ventilators etc and you
know give this department of wicked
risks you know five billion dollars a
year to play with and you know hire in
the most creative most intelligent
scenario thinkers that exist on the
earth to staff it I think that would be
huge for our society that's that's a
great idea and and I think that you know
one of my suspicions of course is that a
lot of the problem in terms of
responding we're having in this Cove in
nineteen crisis is derived from our
current administration but I don't think
this department of what certain things
are not in place that have been in place
before that maybe would have facilitated
things but I but we certainly have is
having as far as I know ever have an
analogue of the department we could risk
in any administration before I think
some companies have such things and I
was reading a nice article about a
grocery store in Texas that's a very big
chain in Texas I forget what it's called
something with an H and it has
essentially this and it and was prepared
for this pandemic in terms of bolstering
its global supply chain storage and so
forth and and is you know it is managing
very well and that's just I love that
story because it's just this you know
it's just I guess not I'm not a huge
company but quite an effective one that
did what our current administration you
know didn't didn't do it all yeah but
the other thing is you know yes it's we
can blame part of it on our
administration in the in the United
States which anyone who listen to the
show knows I'm no great fan of but we
should also note that these systemic
failures of timely action were pervasive
across the West you know
Spain Italy UK France none of them did a
good job of being ahead of the curve the
only people who had did it or did a good
job of being ahead of the curve tended
to be either very small countries like
Denmark or countries who had had
a pre pre run drill on the SARS epidemic
so the eastern rim Taiwan Hongkong
Singapore Japan and to a greater or
lesser degree seem to have done well so
yes we have our special issues shall we
say with our current administration but
the West as a whole failed the test
yeah I think in the United States that's
complicated because I see one of the
great things about the u.s. is this sort
of bottom-up innovation and so everyone
I know you know from CEOs to scientists
is somehow involving themselves and
trying to contribute to Kovan 19 and you
know it's chaotic it's a chaotic semi
coordinated response but it generates a
lot of novel solutions and local
solutions and maybe not you know in this
particular pandemic because of the time
scales you know it's not fast enough but
I think in the we're gonna have to wait
to see whether to sort of partition
partition out these various contributors
to to where we're at today and see how
it plays out down the road and whether
maybe over the longer term this kind of
more you know semi coordinated bottom-up
innovation based strategy that the US
has is useful and I just want to come
back to it's related point come back to
the earlier conversation about building
societies and social structures that
optimize or satisfies robust and evolved
ability as opposed to focus on focusing
on getting specific outcomes like a
degree of inequality it's not just about
you know to have a department of wicked
rest would be awesome and to get people
thinking probabilistically and to think
in terms of scenarios which is a little
different where else to be awesome but I
think there's a much more there's a
profound point philosophically profound
point
hidden in there and that is to really
build a society that optimizes for those
things rather than for inequality we
have to be comfortable with an open
open-ended outcomes because we're not
focusing on specific outcomes like
inequality where we're sort of by
focusing on robustus were saying we're
going to let emerge the right solution
and social structure to combat this
situation
that is not typically even though where
we love innovation here in the States
and we're very bottom-up that that idea
is not a typical idea that I think
Americans are comfortable with
that's classic complexity thinking right
and the number of mature people in power
who are capable of thinking in terms of
complex systems are tiny tiny tiny not
zero but they're very small and you know
to get that kind of responsible we need
to do a better job of selecting leaders
and make sure that they're up to the
snuff to do complexity based thinking
yeah yeah and I mean we but we also need
to sort of come to terms or get
comfortable with the idea that for if we
were to build up this more fluid system
and you know there's all sorts of we
could have a very long conversation very
spective one about how and I will put
some mechanisms on the table in a little
while but we were to build this more
fluid system we'd have to be comfortable
with the possibility that for perhaps a
short time period we might move into a
regime that's a little bit more top-down
we might put in place checks so that
sort of top-down and I'm not you know
I'm not a top-down you know
philosophically oriented person but I'm
you know I'm trying to be objective here
if we if we optimize for buses
availability we have to perhaps accept
that we're sometimes going to enter
regimes that are maybe the best regime
given the environmental challenge we
face but maybe not the most optimal
regime given our sort of underlying you
know our ideas about how we should live
as individuals and what society should
you know what form it should take yeah
we've been talking about this I got some
friends of mine and I and what we think
is that this the kind of meta strategy
is that the system whatever it is this
complex view system for a new social
operating system for our society to be
able to deal with recurrent wicked risks
has to be capable doing phase changes so
it can be in a state that we say honors
all of our deepest values but has to be
able on demand to switch into a new
state literally a new way of operating
called a war fighting mode which may not
be entirely honoring all of our
you know longer-term values but here's
the key you also has to be a reason and
a means by which that times out or which
it returns to its normal mode relatively
quickly once the risk is gone the Roman
Republic had an interesting approach to
this problem and they survived for what
seven hundred years which was that they
had a extraordinarily complicated quasi
democracy quasi oligarchy with all kinds
of different veto points in the system
however by a I think that is some super
majority of the Senate and not vetoed by
the tribunes the the governance
mechanism could appoint a dictator
that's literally what they were called a
dictator the term lasted only exactly
six six months and at the end of that
term the dictator was thrown out of
office and that's how they did the phase
change obviously we could do something
more intelligent but I think that's kind
of the idea you were talking about there
right yeah and in nature you know
receives sort of two different types of
phase changes or transitions in physics
the concept is called a critical point
where they're small perturbation or
small shock to the system because of
long-range correlations kind of big
effects and kick you into a new state
and sometimes we see a repertoire of
state so like the canonical example is
the fish school or the fish swimming
together and they're swimming together
initially in a console where they're
loosely aligned and foraging and then a
predator appears one of the fish detects
the predator and this information
spreads across the group and because
they're they're sitting close to the
tipping point by by shoaling by having
this sort of like low level of alignment
they're able to transition quickly into
the schooling state where they're all
highly aligned and escape the predator
and it's a reversible state change they
can go back to showing so there the fish
have these two these two phases
essentially they have the schooling and
the shoaling and there's a mechanism
that allows them to move between the
school and the shoaling depending on the
detection of the predator and of course
this is a little bit dangerous because
if the fish shoot it initially detects
the predator or thinks there's a
predator present has gotten it wrong
they might switch the schooling
inappropriately so that's the kind of
robustness
of sitting near the critical point but
on the other hand it allows them to
enter a more adaptive state if the fish
really is present right so that's one
where we have that's one example where
we have these two sort of known States
at the Irate level each of which is
adapted to a different environment the
presence or absence of the fish but in
other cases it might be that you sit
near the critical point and you're you
know you you're-you're and you keep your
interactions and your style your
strategies are well tuned to the current
environment but then the environment
changes and it's uncertain or changes to
a distribution that you haven't observed
before and now you enter a state where
that you haven't been for you or you
enter a kind of search space and you
don't know what you're going to get what
you get though you know that what you
had before is inappropriate though
that's the key yeah we talked about we
use in our game be world that we're
liminal to mean that where you enter a
space where you know it ain't what it
was but you're not sure what it is yet
and you know that is a most interesting
space and I think for the things you're
talking about is it probably a good way
to think about the problem you know the
the you know the famous formation
switching by birds and by fish you know
they're quite simple you know a simple
way of relating it's either A or B and
you know the rule for triggering a and B
is quite simplistic as humans we could
be way smarter we can allow ourselves to
be in a liminal space for a while and we
can figure out what's going on you know
and you know those are the kinds of
capabilities that we really need to bake
into our social operating system
well I another you know just again sort
of playing with these ideas when things
are going well actually might be the
time if we could engineer these emergent
systems to you know to induce that state
change to this more elemental phase so
we could explore relatively low cost
sort of like roughly analogous to a
neutral network in biology because for
relatively low cost alternative
solutions and ways of doing things and
then switch back to the one that we know
who works in the given environment it's
not really great to experiment when when
the environment is on
with the exception being that if you
know what you're doing before isn't
gonna work in the current environment
then you have no choice and I just want
to put on the table like a few
mechanisms and again just these are just
mechanisms I've kind of like been I've
been thinking a little bit about my own
head I haven't worked on them and I
don't know if they would work but just
as examples of how we might and you know
in DC state changes I'll take markets as
my starting point yeah let's go for it
I'd love to hear these okay so so one
thing I was thinking about and I have to
I think have two examples one thing I
was thinking about is so the market you
know and I don't know the history of
this yeah I'm working on it the market
has these circuit breakers and the
circuit breakers I think they you know
the circuit breakers stop trading
essentially after there's been a drop of
some magnitude for fifteen minutes or
something like that and and there's a
lot of criticism of these circuit
breakers and I have - one of the things
I haven't determined yet maybe you know
Jim I I don't is what the history on
this is and how well studied this
particular solution is you know
theoretically in mathematical modeling
and empirically like is where did this
idea come from it's an interesting idea
but it seems quite crude to me on the
surface and so one thing I was just
playing around with and again this is
just literally like no work on this it's
just something that's occurred to me
because of the the ability now to
measure the emotional valence in the
population via social media so
computational story lab at UVM I know
you know those guys Peter Dodson and
crew have this domitor that they use to
measure the sort of emotional valence of
people using Twitter and sadly I think
they detected recently the the longest
concerted sad period in their 12 years
of monitoring this but one of the things
I was one of the ideas I was kind of
playing around with the other days what
if you tethered or you made your market
tethered the sort of market management
strategy to something like the domitor
so that when you know the emotional one
of the things that supposedly drives big
drops and markets and maybe in bubbles
in the other direction is is the
emotional states of traders in the
community animal spirits as john maynard
keynes called it the animal spirits
right you get these
her defects hurting effects and
contagions and I think all that used to
be better studied but let's say that
that is correct and roughly and and that
you know these big drops are traders
following the herd essentially causing
the very thing they fear through
feedback what if you tethered the market
to a high domitor so that when you you
can implement maybe like shorter uh you
could implement time windows on trading
or control the number of sales or
whatever given what the emotional
valence was in the population of course
you have to take into account delays and
many things and you might let it sort of
run freely when things are going well
but when the high domitor sorts it
starts to indicate that you know things
are getting a little boisterous or there
or there
you know or there or there or fears
taking over you might you know turn that
knob a little bit interesting idea you
need this you needs a huge amount of
work and you know empirical and
theoretical work but you could sort of
tether things like markets to semi
exogenous data sources like this and
another I'll just put the other one on
the table before you know I we tell me
you know what you think these things are
if you have any ideas of your own I'm
sure you do
ISM is the role of noise and so often
you know noise I worry a lot about noise
and randomness and how it impedes
information processing and biology and
effects you know are nature's ability to
build systems that are well tuned to the
environment cuz basically you see errors
and information processing all over the
place and you can imagine one reason why
that's the case is that the world is
complex and right it's hard to estimate
regularities so noise is often thought
of as something that's problematic and
needs to be overcome and I think about
in those terms lot but noise is also
useful and that's one example there's a
recent study in Nature Physics that I
quite liked by this by Vishu goo tal and
his team and they showed in fish again
that so the fish this is one particular
species of fish that these fish actually
when they're when they're not then
they're sort of misaligned then the
noise in the misalignment feeds back on
itself making
more making bigger fluctuations in their
swimming
trajectories and actually eventually
tips them into an aligned state so the
fish are you know copying or taking into
account what their neighbors are doing
but that is not what causes them to
become aligned what causes them to come
to become aligned is this feedback and
the noise amplifying itself so noise is
potentially a mechanism that could be
added to markets or other phenomena to
help with tuning and you know you just
often don't think in those terms and
that's you know kind of an out of the
box so it's like not an interest rate
but you know adding randomness so the
whoever controls the market would add
some random trades that would be a
really crude first pass example of
people to talk to about that would be
don't farmer and the other guys over and
I met at Oxford but we were working when
I was at an SFI a lot of my work was
done with the automated trading stuff
and we actually actually specialized in
the combination of human-like strategies
with noise traders and I could vary the
ratios and see how the systems responded
it was interesting it was some level
noise traders acted as food to strategic
traders which is laughing and it's
interesting yeah what would happen if
the market goes crazy I'm just gonna
we're getting this out cuz this idea is
actually clever so let's say the the
Federal Reserve's is for lack of any
other entity is looking at the markets
and sees the markets appear to be
overreacting for whatever reason and
they just start introducing a bunch of
noise traders you know literally now
people who buy and sell the algorithm is
ridiculously easy to create a noise
trader and then the noise trader will
actually provide food for other traders
and will tend to cause the market to
stabilize I believe that is true it's
it's been 15 years since I did this work
but Dunn and his folks might actually be
able to provide you with some at least
modeling confirmation of that but I like
this that's very clever out-of-the-box
linking yeah I mean I mean there's a
couple possibilities I think this is not
trivial at all one is well there already
are noise trade
already in the market and it's called
civilians
yeah the mom-and-pop traders yeah ba ba
ba traders are actually actually they're
worse than noise traders all the in all
the evidence shows that they are
considerably worse than noise traders on
an average yeah so it means you have to
drop Plus you have noise traders you
have this incentivizes the very smart
active managers to start trading right
because they see the markets now
becoming a little bit inefficient but
it's also disrupting the signal right
the strong downward signal so I don't
know I think it's non-trivial the other
beautiful thing about noise trading is
it's very inexpensive because you're not
making any bets on the trade you're just
basically buying and selling on both
sides and so all you're doing is paying
the spread and in today's world of
highly automating the spread is tiny so
I could be making you know a hundred
thousand dollar bets repeatedly for
probably less than a hundred dollars
right so the actual cost of the Fed to
introduce noise and in fact today being
paid for putting a limit order on the
book particularly in turbulent times the
goddamn Fed might actually make money
off of it if I love this idea I'm gonna
I'm gonna see if I get somebody to
simulate it they could just pour on the
noise and dampen the signal but you know
coming back to our serve our initial
discussion before we started recording
about this about having a principled
strategy space or family of models for
thinking about the Cova nineteen crisis
you know in the market or economic
portion this is what I would like to see
some out-of-the-box mechanisms like in
addition to the circuit breaker
you know tying to the hydrometer noise
injecting noise you know I just like to
see and maybe you know one thing to keep
in mind is it could be shown in some
cases that some of these are
mechanistically distinct but
mathematically isomorphic so that's
another set of interesting questions but
yeah these are the kinds of things that
are Department of Rickard wicked risks
ought to be working on yeah exactly and
yet nobody's working on it as we know in
our kind of bland dumb short-term
thinking world and that's what we gotta
change there is this I did hear a little
bit about this new exchange called
is it's called the long-term exchange
the do you know this yeah so it's um the
long-term stock exchange what do they do
long-term stock exchange looks new is on
a mission to enable 21st century
companies thrive and I think it favors
like direct listings over traditional
IPOs and I don't know what this try it
doesn't have much information on this
website but apparently it's been
approved as the newest Stock Exchange by
the SEC cool have to look into it again
innovation good thing all right smart
innovation at least and take measured
risks but take risks a little bit a
little bit of a move in the direction
that we're talking about but what would
it take I mean what would it take
because I do I do think that there's you
know quite a deep philosophical issue
here to get people to be comfortable
with open-ended the possibility of
open-ended systems that might change
temporarily and like you say we need to
build mechanisms to make sure these base
changes are reversible but temporarily
into into into structures that maybe
aren't our ideal and I think one thing
we need to do also is have like
mechanisms to support to make sure that
the bottom never drops beyond a certain
level so maybe like these would these
mechanisms this more open-ended
situation or optimizing for buses and
evolvability would require that that we
have you know a standard for quality of
life that must be met we're in this
system a minimum standard for quality of
life and something I don't want like you
know be you know basic Universal income
falls into this space and the idea of a
Welfare Society but I want to get away
from the notion that this would be a
welfare sykes I don't talking about
isn't isn't that at all but I do think
we need to have like we need to maintain
some minimum level hopefully high
quality of life and and then the operand
would be open so in that in in such a
scenario there could be huge inequality
but if everybody's if the lower bound is
high enough perhaps that huge inequality
would not matter so much yeah I
absolutely agree on the first part I am
much less sanguine that the huge
inequality is actually you
for certain amount of inequality is
useful my magic number is about a factor
of 20 from in fact I would have a very
very very aggressive tax routine such
that once you get the twenty times the
minimum wage your tax at about 90% but
anyway that's a difference of opinion
you know but I do think the first part
would make the the ability if people
knew that they personally were safe they
were going to have an income that they
could have medical care they could
afford what they needed to take care of
their kids people would be more willing
to allow more experimentation with some
of the knobs I think right and just to
reiterate again I think what I'm sort of
proposing here is we're optimizing or
satisficing for a bus and evolvability
we're maintaining a lower bound that's
hopefully reasonably high quality of
life but we're leaving this the upper
bound open and so that's why I push back
a little bit on the inequality thing
because it's not that I think large
inequality is useful or not it's that I
want to allow all of these possibilities
just maintain the lower bound right and
so I mean obviously and they might mean
it might be the case that you could not
maintain a high enough lower bound with
very large inequality that might be the
case I don't know but the proposal is
instead of tuning for a particular
outcome you tuned for robust and
evolvability maintaining that lower
bound good place to start I think with
that we're gonna wrap up this has been
as I knew it was gonna be an amazing
intellectual ride lots of new things to
think about lots of things to research
and as usual we'll have pointers to
these various references on the the
episode page so thank you Jessica it's
been great pleasure to be on the show
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
jerod Jane's consulting music by Tom
Muller at modern space music com
[Music]